hello everybody thanks for tuning in to
this ongoing
dialo go sir
about dialogue as we all kind of code
discover what it is that that's for
being here which is really exciting for
me it's been such a pleasure so just
some housekeeping I have a circling
training which is the main thing that I
teach through the circling Institute and
the deadline to register for that it's
happening here in the Bay Area
and the deadline I think is like the
second week of March or something like
that
so if you're interested in in that
there's a link to the circling Institute
below just click that where it says AOC
the art of circling and it'll give you
all information and and we can we can
have somebody contact you if you want to
talk about it let's see what was that
what else was there oh also I do work
with people one-on-one of which people
have been asking me about it please
email me my emails below if you're
interested in that and I think that's
all so this is as I talked about before
this this this conversation with Leah
which is really fun and really awesome
it was cool to to to be to be in the
presence and to be participate in him
coming into this kind of forum and I
think I think you'll find him if you
haven't watched the first video this is
the second part of that video so I'm
doing except this is a little
differently like with the super long
ones I got a lot of feedback where
people are just daunted by the the
length of the conversation so I figure
I'd give it a shot at it
the longer ones is just maybe cutting
them in two so that it's a little bit
more manageable time wise I've also
gotten some feedback that you don't
think that's a really good idea so I
mean I'm new at this and we're all
finding this you know I'm kind of
finding out how to do this I'm in a way
that that that I don't know is is the
most beneficial for everybody
so we'll see how this works so this is
the second part of that conversation
with Leo and
I have found him to be really delightful
to talk talk to in many ways he's got a
like clearly a depth of knowledge and
insight and what we really got deep into
was the how that depth in that knowledge
really arises out of presupposes and
embodies a sense of love and you can
kind of see with Leo I was really struck
by the way he how he said what he said
and all of the the body language and is
pacing and he is kind of muscle there's
like certain street smarts grittiness um
but it kind of like an intimacy there so
it's it was just really great it was
great getting to know him and I look
forward to continue to come to talk with
them so enjoy this conversation this is
part two and really really awesome life
okay
it kind of like it if it requires that
like the giving up of agency or
sovereignty and in the act I think what
wasn't it wasn't it James Joyce had a
lot to say about this at that sense of
we're talking about the I think it was
Joyce that was talking about the
difference between like pornography
right right
and by fine art and he said like fine
art fine it's something about about
something really artful is it it seems
to create this this this spacing
question right that that isn't
immediately intelligible but draws in a
mutual intelligibility right that that
Oaks evokes to participation whereas
with and I think Weber was it that the
sociologist Weber who do then kind of
took that and he this is where he saw
television was dangerous as it removes
he his thought was it removes that space
of reflection yeah
do you literally get taken on this ride
right yeah it's and then you you get
taken off and there's no you just you
didn't have any of that kind of sense of
having to grapple and articulate and to
see and to struggle right there's no
reaching yeah it's like being spoon-fed
right yeah totally you know so here's a
meal that you then can you eat right is
here you go right every bite for you
everything just hey deliver to you
there's no effort there's no nothing
it's just pure sensation yes
since void of perception yes right I
mean this is like a joke I talk about
confirmation porn right like the way in
which you know we love to read things
that tell us what we know already I make
it a point for example like if you're
reading something and
if you're not disagreeing with it all
right or learning something for the
first time oh then you're wasting your
time right right right yeah like if it's
if he was like yeah mm-hmm yeah mm-hmm
that you just wasted that time there's
nothing you've done it you've
accomplished nothing right right right
right because if you disagree with it
well hopefully it's forcing you to
contextualize it right Wow why this that
you know that challenge or it's
something you hadn't considered thought
you're learning something different and
that's what you can reread write some
books reward lots of rereading because
every time you read them you're learning
something else yeah right yeah I'm not
saying you can't do that but I'm saying
is we spend entirely too much time hit
deep in confirmation for it right that's
what Facebook is for the most part right
that's what the algorithm does this guy
likes this thing you know I I've taken
great pride that I've turned my facebook
almost entirely to dogs that mean it
means that after getting grumpy with all
the stuff I was seeing a Facebook I just
went on like a three-month project of
liking or loving only dog pictures now
all facebook gives me is dog pictures
[Laughter]
like I mean that's kind of in my view
inappropriate use of Facebook it's good
for cool I hadn't seen that picture of a
dog before it's eliminating this what
would you call it this opponent opponent
processing well a poodle processing is
important right face by virtue of its
very shell of feedback loop yeah give
you any of that right you get or it
gives you the opposite there's one of
two things that it'll give you right
it'll give you something that you agree
with right directly bla this is you know
this belief you have here it is
yeah they also believe this says dr.
so-and-so or so-and-so or whatever right
or John Q public er or whomever right or
it's an outrageous cartoon of the
opposite which you can safely scorn
right it feeds it hits your rage button
unless you get angry which is also a
form for nog rafi right and and and and
but it's a nice straw man it's easy to
knock down it's like oh it's very stupid
and whatever and you can sort of mock it
and there you go and that's I mean we're
not little they don't develop terribly
sophisticated profiles right they're
just doing what is gonna keep your
attention yeah right yeah so you know
and also I mean not for nothing it's not
like Facebook is in the business of like
cultivating human virtue right so I mean
the day their goal is is to you know
maximize their value for the
shareholders fine that's do you think
right but hmm I'm trying to be like a
reasonably educated consumer of these
things yeah and and so I mean it seems
we live in a world in which so social
media is is a thing and I remember this
I try not to be too much of a little
weird curmudgeonly what I about this
stuff I mean I remember parents coming
to me our MSN my children aren't MSN oh
my god how show me how to block MSN from
my house yeah a number of town hall
meeting type things guess what guys
that's not gonna work I mean I can show
you how to set up your router listen the
other but I can also show you how your
kid can circumvent that in two seconds
by putting the you know the paperclip
and the reset button and is recently
freaking rather yes it's yes this is
this only works until the kid is
sufficiently motivated to do what they
want
Yeah right like that's the the NSA is
not giving you like high tech anything
like these routers are made for
cretinous right even the very fancy ones
as they should be right they're meant to
do they're not meant to substitute your
moral judgment right they're meant to
just connect you on the Internet
like you could your time could be much
better spent instead of trying to thwart
this thing that's never-ending battle
right you know sticking your fingers and
holding the dam and trying to plug every
leak and your fingers pretty quick or
get a freaking msn account figure out
what what's working here and what's
happening and do something with your kid
yeah yeah right yeah help guide your kid
through the Emerson experience yeah when
my oldest my oldest became an digital
citizen around the time when MSN was a
thing huh right and asked me for for a
computer I don't know 10 years old
mm-hmm I thought about it I put one
together and and I had a couple of
simple rules and the thing here is I say
this and some people here there was like
oh my god that's that's crippling like
no no sorry I know rules like tablets
graven you know the holy fire that had
to be kept forward for generation to
generation they're starting roles at
rare meeting wheels on the bike like I
say isn't yeah and so it was it was real
simple
it was remember that this isn't your
computer it's mine uh-huh so I get to
look at it whenever I want yes and if
there's ever a reason that you feel the
need to that bothers you we need to
understand why because it might be a
legitimate privacy issue which is cool
but it also might be that you do is
something that you shouldn't be doing
[Laughter]
rule 2 is you're only allowed to be
friends with people and I'm assume that
you know day to day huh
okay that's just the way it is that goes
away and you have to announce that one
inevitably people have to learn how to
make friends online I mean look at us
right but initially for a ten-year-old
that's a pretty good rule
yeah yeah right and lastly you not
allowed to fight if you find yourself
getting into an argument about something
your father says
that you have to write my father says
I'm not allowed to argue let's talk
about this tomorrow when we see each
other at school that's awesome
those are my rules yeah that's awesome
right and I did all the things you're
not supposed to do I let the kid keep
the computer in their room yeah that's
you know late but I I mean you have to
cultivate trust with your kids right
right
like there's no you don't you don't do
that without trusting honestly this is
the thing is people have weird ideas of
leaving nothing to chance if it's
chanced my friend cognitive finitude is
such that you don't know what's going to
happen anything that you try and do that
you think is gonna take control stuff is
doomed to failure right right so you
gotta lean into the trust into things
totally in fact is it's kind of like
that's I think it's it's uh it always
struck me that like Trust is living like
Trust is a living thing it's not
I trust you or I don't it's like I trust
you something happens if draws it into
question and then we look at it and we
work something out right they can review
it and heal and grow and become stronger
and the stress can make it actually even
more powerful and like there's
organizing even break right from the
term it becomes what yeah but here's the
thing
it's a simple link like the thing that I
think that I did and convinced this is
different from the way a lot of people
parented but I could be wrong so I don't
want to go on record or saying I'm so I
don't want to claim unique convention or
authorship but I feel this is different
about the way I was pretty young when my
first kid came around like Holloway 22
when they were born and I was an
unemployed high school dropout
like it was like yeah yeah like not a
trivial thing
so one of the ways that I got myself
through this right every day was a gut
check
right because we are will Safed it
fairly early in the process so I had
like a good nine months of like wow this
is what's happening right I think nine
months after it happened to kind of even
comprehend that something had happened
well so I one of things that I did is
the only way would make sense to me was
to formulate this as a finite goal okay
so I was like I have a clear goal yeah
when this creature is 18 years old it
will be able to take responsibility for
its own happiness that's my goal
Wow that doesn't mean that I will vanish
from their life it just means that I'm
trying to create a self-sufficient being
I'm not I I wasn't buying into I'm going
to like guard this thing for life
I mean partially yes right I left my son
I will I would happily drop the entire
world a meat grinder for him yeah yeah
without question of that hesitation
without horror dread just no no all of
you could buy genocide like that's there
but I wasn't yeah but here's the thing I
love my boy but he's got his own life he
lives his life well and he's good I
don't bother him but what he's doing
yeah I mean like we we have a very good
close relationship
well said he's an agent he's an
independent agent I have no interest in
telling what to do dude I mean that
would fort the project that I'd put so
much time and effort into which was
helping to foster an agent yeah
individual person yeah right so when you
see it that way instead of this weird
like we mythologize we make a cartoon of
how dangerous the world is oh my god and
we're like in her to like and you need
the flash cards and the best teachers
and the this and everything it Evans
already perfect you know anything up and
and there can't be so much as a bruise
and like you try and and and and you try
and take
control the universe and bend it around
your child and it's it's just stupidly
more prevalent it seems to me like like
even just in my lifetime I've noticed
I've noticed in the last I don't ten
years that it's almost like weed I think
Heidegger was really prophetic around
this it's like we don't you don't really
like see our kids and see an individual
that will then do difficult things and
strive and develop character we see we
see them as like a kind of standing
reserve with a bunch of resources that
we can obviously if right treasure
waiting to be despoiled and taken from
us yeah dude it's like and so I mean I
always structured my parenting around
the goal of my kids eventual
self-sufficiency
yeah yeah right they built that from day
one yeah it was the only way it could
make sense of what was happening and how
I was going to go forward and here's old
and and having having being a high
school dropout in order to make sense of
this thing you can like really show up
for and like yeah right well in in in in
to do like like I had to confront like I
had no faith in my own father and what
he was and how he had been and I just
knew that couldn't be that but that like
knowing what not to be isn't telling you
what to do yeah right and so I had no
choice but to think about it really like
put time and effort into formulating the
project of parenthood
you know I'm imagining that was a just
that like one seeing that necessity
right and then responding to it in the
way that you did I would I just get the
sense that that was probably pretty
transformative for you yeah
absolutely like yeah I said earlier in
that that you know I think that my kids
saved my life like I think that huh I
mean at the time I was unemployed high
school drop it I don't know that I would
my trajectory would have altered
tremendously for the better if I hadn't
had a kid then Yeah right on the other
hand well cuz it I clearly wasn't
motivated for my own sake right it
wasn't like I hadn't at that point
figured out how to have put together a
useful life for myself
like I said on my own merit for myself
right it was the realization that I was
responsible for this person that was
like oh okay right you know the kids not
gonna have a loser for a father like
that's just
yeah that's not gonna happen right and
you know and not even just in a trivial
sense not like I don't make kid to be
ashamed I mean I have to be useful I
have to put myself in a place where I
have the knowledge skills and resources
to do accomplish this the best like
right right and and it was you know I
had always been a person that people
referred to as having potential before
then alright that's a crappy gifted
class word potential yes
you know I guess but it was Rowan who my
son out of everyone at have any teacher
in my life who showed me how to turn
potential into into actual right right
Wow and is that how so now like do you
teach at the University you heard you
talk about like high school kids I've
done at this point like everything from
elementary to graduate school so the
last teaching I did the last teacher he
did was at U of T at Oise and should say
specifically which is a school within
University of Toronto so I was teaching
actually teaching so I was teaching the
teachers college and I was teaching
psychological foundations of learning
and development for education so
basically trying to teaching the
psychology that that teachers ought to
know right but also giving them a bag of
tricks right like I mean that's kind of
what everyone in Teachers College wants
from you is a bag of tricks am I going
to be in a room full of kids what do i
do how do I do this that the other and I
tried to formulate the class as sort of
like here's the value of understanding
theoretical psychology right this is how
this makes you this is the lens that it
gives you to look at things and how it
affords your problem-solving because
you're thinking for a problem-solving
perspective you've already failed like
it's problem-solving is is is a side
effect of mastery yes
right yes don't worry about the
problem-solving yes in the mastery right
because if you're asking me well what do
I do when this has happened well it
seems to me that you do everything wrong
from beginning so the solution to this
problem is not having done all these
things back then yes you always find
problems to solve right and this lens
will help you do that but more than that
it teaches you how to do things you
don't have those kinds of problems to
solve yeah yeah simple things to like
start strict all right it's always easy
it's easier to go from being maybe a
little bit too strict and relaxing a bit
than it is to go from an unstructured
place and try an odd structure that's
yeah like it just doesn't work it
doesn't work right so always start
things a little bit formal a little
tight a little bit over right and then
relax into the class relax into the room
that also mirrors the normal process of
development of intimacy right you begin
with a handshake you in with the hug
right that's fine right if you start
with the hot hugs
then hugs was currency right and then
sincerity is for the questioning and
then just things disintegrate and no
trust and this is the thing this is true
for parenting too by the way
right a lot of parents try and be their
kids friends oh right they did they okay
that's unfair and then sorry let me
reframe that and rewind a bit it's not
that people try to be their kids friends
that's a bit of a hacky trope what it is
is that our best heuristic to diagnose a
relationship with a given person all
right is how pleasant the interaction is
yeah okay that's a very common simple
and pervasive heuristic all right yeah
so we do that with our kids we do that
with anyone right now
that sort of is a very superficial
metric right and it looks best in
reciprocal relationships in a reciprocal
relationship if you're mad at me as an
independent adult agent so you
independent adult agent are mad at me
independent of agent that means
something right I have trespassed on you
or so there's something right a kid can
be mad at you because you imposed a
bedtime which we all know is really
important right they have they lack the
frontal lobe to realize they're gonna be
a complete like just useless in the
morning if they don't so you know if you
were to use that heuristic then well the
kid hates you oh my god this this
relationship is in crisis right no
because I'm not an adult right like it's
so the thing is though is that's a very
it's often very easy to to repair a
situation if that's the metric you're
using yeah yeah yes yes yes totally yes
so thing is over time you see the kids
gravitate to the person who gives them
stretcher I've said this before a lot of
kids act out not because they want to
break out of your arms because they want
to feel your arms around them holding
them containing the chaos yeah yep it's
it's it's it's not it's it's not an act
of repudiation or rebellion or one it's
just okay good it's like sometimes you
check the table to see how firm it is
yes
absolutely absolutely on a sense that's
that's a really important thing like
when you're a kid for a large part of it
like your parents are the pillars of
reality for God's sakes like they're
like you know you don't want your the
pose of reality to fold like a cheap
suit and give you ice cream for dinner
every night that's a pretty this is
simply a pillars speaking of that that
which can like that sense of tolerating
the conflict right standing in as they
hate you and all the different versions
of that like that's the part like I'm
imagining because you said you said your
dad yet like you didn't you didn't have
a whole lot of respect for your dad I
had sort of a contentious relationship
with my father
absolutely yeah so is it is it fair to
say in some ways learning to be a dad
yeah this is stuff that you've had to
just is it you I didn't really think
through it and look and contend with it
because it wasn't just my the history
that Greg could it couldn't be monkey
see monkey do Yeah right it couldn't be
like oh well you know this is what
happened I could go okay I don't do this
like my dad from my dad I got one and
actually I would argue like the
chorister most basic lesson right and at
the essence at the very base of it you
know the thing that my kids need from
what anything else is the feeling of
safety oh okay so Papa safe no matter
what Papa might be angry Papa might be
this pop like whatever but safe you're
safe with me right yeah and in that
sense of safety has to - has to whether
things like I'm drunk and I don't know
where I am and I needed help getting
home right calling me should be a
natural response for my kids in that
situation right not I
my dad can never know about this yeah
they should be my dad is my best shot
here like you know yeah like that
cultivating that sense of safety right
and that's and that's troops and
educator as well right because at the
end of it like learning I mean is
learning is making mistakes until you
make less mistakes that's basically it
is is is it's it's just like it's a
really long chain of right and
what you're doing is you're slowly
reducing the frequency and the scale of
the yeah yes that's that's a
pretty hairy experience we think of it
right great
like that's so I mean a teacher has to
deliver error signal in a way that
doesn't just shut someone down yeah that
makes them wanted to keep coming back
because in particular you need people to
do that for things they don't want to do
right because very few people are
intrinsically motivated to practice
multiplication tables right there's most
of the good things you learn are not
things that you would have chosen to do
on your own dude I mean let's do let
kids decide or choose mmm no because
what happens is then people just do the
things they do Socratic ly happen to
think they're good at yes right and they
never push or challenge themselves or
grow right no one ever became a complete
person just by sticking to their
strengths yeah yeah
yeah I always have to do a challenge yes
so I mean there you go so teaching is
convincing some do submit alike all
right and to do it in criminally less
pulley over a long period of time right
frame that way it's I think I think as
I'm learning more about about you and
just like his more of your life is just
kind of naturally revealing stuff in the
conversation I'm I'm becoming I feel
like when I think about now what you
talked about in the very beginning in
conversation about like yeah kids having
kids Ben
most crucial thing in my life like it's
important and I had no way of knowing
that beforehand in fact I thought I
wouldn't do I shouldn't have kids but
now it's just obvious like in fact yeah
and it's been becoming a father so when
I think about you becoming a father here
it's interesting cuz I would say that
like it doesn't seem it doesn't seem
just given to me that like because
there's a lot of there's a lot of men
who have kids that like to have fathers
or ignore it didn't respond to it like
you are right right and I think what I'm
wondering about like I'm struck by that
I'm like it's not just given that if you
have enough necessity ie a kid that
you'll go pump let's define this what am
i what is really worth like that
response to doing that is that I'm
wondering about like is that connected
to the love that we've been talking
about absolutely looks like it's not
love that had it's not out of like meat
like being near that or being shown that
or having experienced that no no no
that's love for my child love you know
it's yeah like I said love is that
wonderful thing that Orient's you
towards things about how unpleasant they
can get no matter how challenging no
matter how terrifying it is yeah
right I mean it's funny it with have you
ever had an experience where you have
dreaded a thing you do to be squeamish
about everything and then it happened
and you just did it and it just happened
and you're like okay I did that like
alright it's not a challenge anymore
yeah it's like yes that's I mean
certainly actually it's like circling
for me it was like that like it was this
thing that kind of happened
spontaneously and we started doing it
like let's keep moving towards it
and there's a there was a certain moment
where we were circling it didn't even
have a name at that point but doing we
were finding what it was that we saw and
just trying to like get closer to it and
there's this one moment where we were
circling and this woman dropped in this
traumatic experience oh wow and I I
looked at my partner I was doing it with
Jerry and he just went he kind of like
turned white and then just faded the
background and I looked around and I had
no idea what to do but I had a moment
where I didn't get to not know what to
do
yeah right and I just like that moment
in necessity is something I would never
like volunteer for but like it at the
moment has it ended like enough
necessity where I was like I just didn't
have the option of not knowing what to
do and pulling that and so much of
learning how to circle being developing
is about that particular relationship
and that's what love is but that's what
love does right
love is why you have no you don't have
the option you couldn't let her down
yeah you couldn't yeah yeah yeah like
it's just when someone presents
themselves to you that that
vulnerability and that much need like
what will you do you you you step up you
don't have a choice you like yeah take
them into your arms you do whatever you
have to and you deal and you manage yes
no and and maybe you don't have the
expertise but that's okay right like you
work on it together you you you get to a
place of safety right and then maybe you
can do something better more intelligent
or maybe you did great who knows but
there is a thing it's it's fundamentally
the love that Orient's you towards that
right you know all of its why you know
you fight wild beasts and and and and go
into burning houses and do all sorts of
things right
it's methey way of talking about how you
can transcend her or limitations it's
amazing like it's just this is this this
wonderful motivation and the more that
we can practice it and not you know not
in a silly way like him but I don't a
sound like it's very funny I watched
I just watched the latest Tarantino
movie the other day once once I'm in
Hollywood I'm very aware of the 60s
thing and there's you know the Manson
Family is part of it and the whole
hippie thing and I'm not talking about
trying to talk about love in and I'm not
trying to present myself as some sort of
like well ubiquitously loving guru this
is far from the case but but I can
certainly talk about what what I think
works and what what's good and in what
I'm talking about cultivating love it's
not a sort of a you know tossing flowers
in the air and all linking arms it's
it's finding a way to harness that
incredibly powerful motivation that
connects us to each other right that
creates common purpose out of seemingly
nothing worse than nothing out of out of
out of rage and enmity somehow you love
little common purpose out of that and
and and common purpose of such uncommon
power and and result they're just you
you do things that you didn't think you
could do you know not even not just like
fancy adrenaline things up flipping cars
but like but like delivering a child
when you then when you don't know how
feeling okay you just deal with it
maybe totally were you typically taking
responsibility right right you just like
what I'm hearing is like taking
responsibilities in such a way that what
you respond to is ultimate yeah yeah and
that that I'm just I'm appreciating I
totally get what you mean in a visceral
way when he it's like that you're not
some like Love Guru oh yeah I can feel
like it there's a great there's like
love for you is the thing that has you
deeply involved and wrestling with
things and like one understand why it's
like it seems like it seems like the
thing that hat has you deeply involved
in your world yeah yeah I wanted to talk
cut I want to talk with the feud with a
few minutes that we have left
I wanted to UM talk about I get your
thoughts about you know having liked
working with John right I would imagine
he sounds like you got you've known John
for a hollow award like twenty years
there twenty years so you've known yeah
right and then and then they're like
relatively recently and last whatever
year or so mm-hmm he started he put his
stuff originally put his stuff online
and then he really consciously did it
and had help doing it and it in this in
all these conversations and you're kind
of watching all what has that been like
for you just being his friend and his is
Holly and I mean what's it what how do
you see that how has that impacted you
like what does that reveal to you about
the world right now what does that
reveal to you about what John's doing
and what you're seeing and what you're
all that I mean I want to avoid sort of
foolish hyperbole but and also like I
also don't want let me careful have
frame this because because it it can
come off a little weird but hey I think
John is a very he's a he's a very unique
person and he is I think a significant
thinker I think that John is like an
Aristotle like a Socrates like I think
that he is a thinker in that order
I said that to him before he gets
incredibly embarrassed and doesn't want
to engage with that that's fine that's
cool and nor should he to be honest I
mean it's not even almost like even fair
to say that to a person right like
John's not John's not driven by that
sort of thing right not that he's
flawless and and and and and John can
can have any number of personal flaws
that we all do right
so I'm not trying to like canonize him
not try to you whatever right but I've
felt very privileged to have John as
sort of a mentor in my life right and I
met John when I was an undergrad and I
took its course
and like our relationship has grown
through that like to being colleagues
whatever etc so I mean I find it
gratifying that John has successfully
found a platform to share what he's
doing because part of it the pure
cognitive science part is good it's
useful it's fine it's something I like I
enjoy but I don't know how much the
person the average person gets from that
nor should they write know more than the
average person cares about protein
synthesis mechanism X or whatever or the
other right there's there's a technical
thing which is but in particular in
cognitive science in psychology and what
there's a lot of stuff that we've
learned or we know that just doesn't
somehow percolator get out there I got
different reasons why I think it doesn't
but it's these things that in John's
work when the meaning crisis in
particular is one of those things I
think is important it's something that
is you know I mean he's put his finger
on something yeah yeah and so I mean he
approached this the way he does a lot of
things right he thought about it a lot
right and I mean I've been involved in
some iterations of this and more in some
less than others whatever I was actually
surprisingly saw the first video I'm
gonna call him talk to him whatever and
it's like and it's good and he has I
think successfully carved out a niche
where he's avoiding a lot of the common
pitfalls that you see another another
thing I watched the other day was contra
points latest video I don't know if you
follow contra points on YouTube and all
of you seen I would strongly recommend
them her
she's a she's a fantastic YouTube she's
um she's kind of a very sort of lefty
social justice II person and some people
find that off-putting some people don't
whatever
she deals a lot with trans issues but a
lot of things as well her earlier stuff
is more looking is very political and
looking at you know things to do with
the all tripe and blog but recently has
been dealing more with trans issues and
has is in the midst of being cancelled
as they say and and did a video about it
that was really I did a very brave and
touching to me and watered and also
makes you profoundly grateful that John
is doing this really well because here
you've got this person who has put out
work
I think country points is one of the
most skillful hammers of the point of
view I've seen on the internet like
putting out stuff that has a point of
view there's like you know some people
call it biased I think it's a sort of a
silly term I'm in some cases like and
but somehow managed to be inclusive
despite it so even while saying you know
I don't like fascism not sitting there
being angry and scolding but like hey
how do we look at this differently
whatever really really good good stuff
and and and so clearly a person lacking
malice as far as I can tell anyway right
who has run afoul of his employer I
guess had an opinion or had a couple of
opinions that are not allowed and is now
suffering like the slings and arrows of
social media okay baby like my retinas
and the light and the thing thank you
sure that's great thank you
I love that your life just broke in
right there is awesome I have a wife and
two kids awesome and that's and that is
the most important thing right yeah love
seeing seeing this video bite by this
other person and I really uh like I mean
I think it's inevitable that John's
going to run into problems right because
John also has a point of view Yeah right
yeah but he is doing as he as he
inevitably variably does he's doing this
with great skill and aplomb you know he
puts thought into it it does it and I
hope I hope that it provides some
meaningful basis for change and dialogue
about things I see some people who like
John who I think are missing the point
and are taking things that John says as
confirmation porn in a poor way I see
people who don't like what John says who
are taking him as rage Bates right we
discussed that earlier so the two poles
of Facebook content confirmation porn
and range bait yeah but I see a lot of
people that this is resonating with yeah
and and that's good yeah that gives me a
lot of a lot of hope I mean we're at a
place were at a place where as I said
our full force multipliers are at just
an incredible like once upon a time you
know a king could oppress some peasants
until the peasants all got upset and
then and then the king was like either
it changes ways or he wasn't the king
anymore yeah yeah right
and as we progress in history a king can
push the peasants further
the force multipliers increase right so
more presents can be pissed off more
right you know if if all you've got is
you happen to be the toughest guy in the
village right that's good for pushing
around people so far so much right well
now you've got a group of guys who are
unswervingly loyal to you okay you can
push around more people further
well you've discovered how to how to
forge steel right and and that's a
costly time you know Kazu process so you
have a few guys who have sharp pointy
things that don't break you can push
around even more people even further
right but up until a couple hundred
years ago that was the limit of force
multiplication so yes buddy I'm okay you
wanna come and say hi yeah yeah it's a
big mess in here so you know up until a
couple hundred years ago we're still
basically talking about pointy things
right an armor the stirrup helps you
know those things but like there was
still a very real need to respect the
mass the population yeah it's not truly
more I think it just isn't oh right I
mean the are our weapons are just
unfathomably powerful yeah yeah with
drones and taking all
it's possible to just deliver like
unthinkable payloads of distraction
right with very few people were there a
few agents necessary to do it yeah right
you don't have to count on the loyalty
of an extended network right like you
can like smaller is better for an elite
group right
one minute buddy okay you want to take
the headphones yeah you can take those
in there and then pop the wool will plug
them in for you later okay okay and more
importantly our ability to weaponize
information as well right so I mean in
trivial senses you look at video game
design right and and the way in which
all the things we know you know the best
addiction research has gone not into
curing addiction but into making video
games a money pit yeah right like so and
that's and that's just the most benign
of it right now imagine how that gets
deployed or to to maintain status quo
and power and whatnot right I mean
people people can be convinced to
support things that are not in the best
interest like it's just that easily
simply we can persuade lots of people to
to to act you know in favor of a
privileged few even at their own expense
so those force multipliers are now no
longer just in terms of violence and
physical destruction but in terms of
shaping minds and hearts too and and
what's worse is the consequences of that
technological growth we're sending to
face some of the consequences of the
most readily apparent of those
consequences what's the media of what
you know like climate issues and this
and the other we absolutely need to look
at things in a different way
we absolutely need to look at things in
a different way
and and I think if anyone has a shot
it's John like I said I mean John has
two crucial things he has the vision
first of all I mean he's just an
amazingly powerful thinker right yeah
John also has the ability to make people
care about this stuff to listen to the
teacher yeah you can be as smart as the
day is long if no one cares what you say
who cares
this is meaningless you then yeah and
John has the ability to make this
catching like to make people buy in sign
on and so I mean when I saw him do when
I saw him take Heidegger right yeah and
like one he's out the thing to talk
about ray first of all that's so that's
we've talked a lot about the thing that
amazes me about his teaching is what he
doesn't teach later and like that that
relevant logiss that's relevance
realization right there but just that he
was able to make Heidegger somewhat
accessible to somebody that never even
heard of isn't it optical and hasn't
heard of Heidegger and Dubuque makes
something intelligible that way in a way
that does didn't clock like it the
argument was really deep I would I was
just impressed as hell by that skill
yeah yeah no no he's he's he is like a
mmm I would say more than a generational
thinker like I think he's an epochal
thinker like he's just and and so yeah I
mean you know he's also like when we
very close as best friends yeah and and
so seeing him succeed in this is it's
very gratifying yeah on one level of
what I'm hearing is I get one level how
it's been for you it's like you've been
relating and thinking like God you know
in essence I think my friends another
Socrates and even even that he doesn't
want to engage with that is just more of
why I think he's like they're just sure
that so
so one little unit like just
understanding that and then so to watch
him stepping in the world and watch this
watch this this response that's starting
what becomes possible like oh you're
like of course you'd do that is that is
that I mean I could another time maybe
I got a no there's also want to be
careful because I mean we're recording
and stuff and whatever and I yeah
stories like John John's a funny guy
like there's a and he's it's funny
because John one of John is someone who
is very capable but the funny thing is
is he also underestimates himself a lot
sometimes it's funny to see yeah right
it's not what's what then not just it's
very funny he's yeah he's a trip yes
really
yeah no it's like I said like the the
best like the the best I've been as a
thinker has been with John alright like
being in a row in a room with with John
and Anderson or whomever and whatever
and and talking whatever and things just
things happen it's awesome dude I mean
and and it's like and what you're able
to do is awesome you know I mean John's
a force multiplier that's part of what
makes him that kind of a thinker it's
not just he himself it's not just the
fact that that John has this just
amazingly came sharp discernment insight
whatever said all that stuff it's what
he brings out and the people around him
yeah it's how he evokes and provokes and
and and and fee it's a generates and you
know like I mean
I don't think of myself as a simpleton
but like I'm I'm never as smart as I am
when I'm in a room with John yeah yeah
you know yeah totally
like when we think about it like John
John says is before and we've done
without it's like the whole thing is
this is magical cosmic coincidence that
you know Socrates was blessed with with
the great student Plato and Plato's was
the great student and Aristotle and so
on I don't think that's that sort of
blessing is that a happenstance right
the truly greater teachers yeah like the
greatest thinkers are teachers and the
best teachers cultivate that dude I mean
like that's that's how you know that
someone was great because look at this
dude I mean it it had a footprint
outside their own skull yeah yes which
is one of the things that's just really
a igniting I think and exciting about
this like what we're doing right now in
being and and and having like found John
and and and then all the people around
right I'm just it's it's been an
incredible thing to be a part of and
deeply validating in the sense of having
a similar intuition there's something
profound that happens in relationship in
dialogue that is like that is like is
goes so far beyond what seems like is
acceptable and available like the
possibility in relationship like kind of
like what you're talking about is being
a father and a right did say something
to me right and they could absolutely
like completely radically change my life
right you could hear something in me
like that I didn't understand and point
it out and it could completely enlighten
me or it could like traumatized me yeah
I'm thin about it's like it feels like
like that somehow in the times that
we're in one of the rare places that it
seems like we could still have gods
users if right so to speak is in this in
subjective connection and everything
that that can afford and I just like the
sense of like that we're finding seems
like we're finding away and what John's
doing with the after Socrates and was
circling and and all this stuff around
the meeting crisis is what's really
beautiful is watching how technology
actually seems to have afforded write
something that which is is kind of rare
that something very untechnical which is
these long meandering kind of Socratic
interpersonal conversations then other
people can watch and participate in and
respond to and then there's something
about this that just has my attention to
kind of glows it glows out for me yeah
to me it makes so much sense I mean yeah
how does it how does it make sense to me
but you when you think about about the
flow state of flow experience yeah right
one of the things that you need to
trigger that alright is is a complex
context yeah you need a dynamic changing
challenge right there is nothing that
presents a more complex challenge
another person it's that simple right
like it's it's just this is like it like
anyone you look at there you're looking
at a buttload of snakes but I mean
anyone is capable of saying a thing as
you said that just changes your whole
life you know and and so having a good
conversation having is you know because
also what it does to you right
look we're cognitive misers right the
more we stay in our head I think the
brain trends to automaticity alright
there's there's a powerful cost
reduction function at working your
great brains most metabolically
expensive piece of meat in your body
this is people like reliably people lose
weight and exam season right when
they're studying even though they're
there they're being practically sessile
it's like it doesn't matter how low your
present
your brain is this incandescent thing
that is just eating all the energy right
so there's a strong cost reducer at work
right and and that automaticity is one
of the ways in which we do that yeah we
learn to make things automatic yeah and
and and and so what happens is is our
intrapsychic understanding gets
short-handed and reduced and
short-handed and reduced and we give
ourselves the benefit of the doubt all
the time and think we understand things
and we give ourselves the
phenomenological experience of
understanding for not enough work and we
just make do but when you're talking to
someone else that doesn't cut it right
and suddenly you have to formulate
things again and suddenly things have to
be made real and critical or whatever
and and that's just talking if the other
person responds and there's an
appropriately Wow and suddenly you know
you've pulled in suddenly you're
actually thinking you're not just you're
not just running a cost reduction
calculus on the minimum of you have
to get the macaroni and cheese in your
face right suddenly it's no no like this
is you know and you can actually open up
the engine a bit and actually engage
right because there's this wonderful
motivational framework attached to it
yeah yes yes right that motivational
framework supersedes the cost reduction
function and there we go hey it's really
it's really great meeting you and and I
have to say so there's there's um what
is I'm just I'm appreciating I'm
appreciating your how transparent you
are and just your way of being like I
just really fighting it like my
and I can totally get that you're an
awesome teacher yeah thank you and I
appreciate and I look forward to more
and more hearing about your life and
what you think and having more patience
if you're up for it
absolutely absolutely yeah how is this
for you
no this is great I've enjoyed myself a
lot I mean I wasn't sure what to expect
but in like I said I mean I prepared
myself a little bit not too much I
didn't want to be it's over rehearsed or
whatever I like I said this this did
strike me as a bottom up and everything
this is good this is a this is a lot of
fun I mean look I like to talk that's
obvious you know so I mean that's never
a bad time for me and and I got a lot
out of it too you know and and and who
knows maybe maybe next time you'll talk
more and I'll shut up a little bit yeah
we'll see thank you so much my pleasure
my pleasure thank you very much take
care what I don't know how this works